Guide to the Robert E. Slye Papers, 1961-2001
NASA Ames History Office
Robert E. Slye Papers
1961-2001
PP07.13-RS
Ames Research Center
Number of containers: 4 Volume: 4.8 cubic feet
Ames Research Center, Ames History Office Moffett Field, California 94035
This collection, accumulated by NASA Ames Research Center scientist Robert E. Slye, consists of reports, research proposals, memoranda, contracts, conference and workshop proceedings, user guides, administrative announcements, newsletters, secondary publications and other materials related to the NASA Mission Analysis Division, technology applications research and general administrative activities.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Related Collections
Larry A. Manning Papers, 1967-1988 (PP05.04)
Donald E. Wilson Earth Resources Survey Program Papers, 1972-1983 (PP07.13-DW)
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Robert E. Slye in August 2007.
Biographical History
Robert "Buzz" E. Slye was born in 1934 in Burlington, Vermont. He received a B.E. in Mechanical Engineering from Yale University in 1956, where he also served in the Reserve Officers' Training Corps. He earned a M.S. in Aeronautical Engineering from Stanford University in 1957. Slye joined NACA Ames Aeronautical Laboratory in Moffett Field, California, in June 1957 as a summer student, and was subsequently assigned to Air Force duty on the Ames campus in the fall of 1957.
As a summer student, and after conversion to a permanent post as research scientist in 1958, Slye worked with Alfred Eggers and Clarence "Sy" Syverston as a member of the 10 x 14 Inch Wind Tunnel Branch (1957 to 1960) and the 3-1/2 Foot Wind Tunnel Branch (1960 to 1963). Here, he was involved in projects relating to the aerodynamics of lifting bodies, rockets and re-entry capsules. In 1963, Slye became a member of the Mission Analysis Division, Space Applications Branch. The Mission Analysis Division's main function was to conduct studies to determine research areas in which Ames could use its time and funds most effectively. Here, Slye became an expert in trajectory analysis, and was involved in conducting studies on the feasibility of transporting humans to the moon and mars, and in conducting shuttle and launch vehicle studies, including trajectory and payload analysis, costing, planning, design and implementation. Slye was a member of the Mission Analysis Division from 1963 to 1969, the System Studies Division from 1969 to 1971, and the Advanced Concepts and Missions Division from 1971 to 1975.
When the Advanced Concepts and Missions Division dissolved in 1975, Slye moved to the Data Research and Management Branch (1975 to 1976), the Technology Applications Branch under the Airborne Missions and Applications Division (1976 to 1984) and later the Ecosystem Science and Technology (ECOSAT) Branch under the Life Science/Earth System Science/Earth Science Divisions (1984 to present). His research activities under these divisions largely relate to the analysis and display of computer information, including remotely sensed images. As a member of the Ecosystem Science and Technology Branch, Slye worked to develop new understandings of the Earth's ecosystems through remote sensing, airborne imaging and data processing research.
Slye's career at Ames has spanned over a half of a century and is remarkable in that he has made important research contributions in a wide range of disciplines. Slye received the NASA/Ames Special Achievement Award in 1988. At the time of his retirement in December 2007, Slye was the longest continually employed worker at Ames. He became an Ames Associate in 2008, and as of November 2009, Slye is listed as an Ames Associate with the Ecosystem Science and Technology Branch.
Sources Consulted:
Bugos, Glenn E. Atmosphere of freedom: sixty years at the NASA Ames Research Center. Washington, D.C.: NASA SP4314, 2000.
Bugos, Glenn E. NASAs 50 Year Men and Women: Buzz Slye in NASA: 50 Years of Exploration and Discovery. NASA, 2008.
NASA Ames History Office, NASA Ames Research Center. Moffett Field, California. AFS1030.39A, Ames Astrogram Collection. 1958-2008.
NASA Ames History Office, NASA Ames Research Center. Moffett Field, California. AFS1070.8A, Archives Reference Collection. Telephone Directories. 1962-2003.
Indexing Terms
The following terms may be used to index this collection.
Personal Name
Slye, Robert E.
Corporate Name
Ames Research Center; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Subjects
Launch vehicles (Astronautics); Trajectory optimization; Payloads (Aerospace engineering); Computer engineering--Data processing; Remote sensing.; Remote-sensing images; Landsat satellites.; Image analysis.; Image processing.; Ecosystem management--Research.; Feasibility studies; Cost analysis
Geographic Names
Moffett Field (Calif.)
Scope and Content
The collection consists of scientific reports, quarterly and annual reports, research proposals, memoranda, correspondence, contracts, studies, secondary publications, conference proceedings, meeting minutes, agendas, newsletters, bibliographies, indexes, directories, rosters, workshop proceedings, user guides, administrative announcements, clippings, ephemera and a transcript of the 1996 NASA Ames "State of the Center" speech. The materials provide insight into Slye's activities with the Mission Analysis Division and Technology Applications/Ecosystem Science and Technology Applications Branches as well as into the administrative activities of NASA Ames.
Series I, Mission Analysis Division Records, 1965-1974, contains reports, proposals, memoranda, secondary publications and other material related to the design, costing, selection and analysis of shuttles and launch vehicles. Series II, Technology Applications Records, 1974-1998, includes reports, memoranda, newsletters, rosters, plans and other materials related to the activities of the NASA Ames Airborne Missions and Applications and Life Science/Earth System Science/Earth Science Divisions. A number of records relate to the Landsat Remote Sensing Technology Program and the Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP). Series III, NASA Ames Administrative Records, 1971-2001, consists of clippings, publications, memoranda and administrative announcements related to topics such as staff honors, organizational restructuring and policies. Series IV, General/Reference Publications, 1961-1999, largely consists of newsletters (generated both by Ames and outside publishers) and secondary publications on topics related to Slye's fields of interest, including aeronautics, remote sensing and computing.
Arrangement of the Robert E. Slye Papers
The papers are arranged into four series:
I. Mission Analysis Division Records, 1965-1974.
II. Technology Applications Records, 1974-1998.
III. NASA Ames Administrative Records, 1971-2001.
IV. General/Reference Publications, 1961-1999.
Materials within each series are arranged chronologically.
Series Description
- Mission Analysis Division Records, 1965-1974; I.; 56 folders
  Series Description
  The materials in Series I reflect the activities of the Mission Analysis Division, System Studies Division, and the Advanced Concepts and Missions Division from 1965 to 1974. Many records relate to Lockheed contract NAS 2-5202, in which methodologies and computer models were constructed for optimal launch vehicle assignment for advanced space missions in light of strict budgetary constraints. According to one of the reports associated with this contract, "a primary objective [of the study] is provision of an analytical tool to help the advance planner to maximize, under restrictive budget constraints, the accomplishment of a future space program." Materials related to the Burner II, Titan/Centaur, Solid/Agena and Saturn family of launch vehicles are included in this series.
- Technology Applications Records, 1974-1998; II.; 44 folders
  Series II consists of records related to the activities of the NASA Ames Data Research and Management Branch, Technology Applications Branch and Ecosystem Science and Technology (ECOSAT) Branch from 1974 to 1998. Here, Slye was involved in performing research in ecosystem science, remote sensing, and computational image analysis. Many materials relate to the Landsat Remote Sensing Technology Program and the Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP). Slye was particularly involved in remote sensing, airborne imaging, and data processing research. Research subjects include coastal-zone, forestry, geography, geology, hydrology, meteorology, oceanography, agricultural and fire studies.
- NASA Ames Administrative Records, 1971-2001; III.; 11 folders
  Series III consists of records on topics such as exhibits, personnel appointments, policies, Ames events and activities, length of service honors, branch/division restructuring and other organizational changes, and a transcript of the 1996 "State of the Center" address by Director Ken K. Munechika.
- General/Reference Publications, 1961-1999; IV.; 40 folders
  Series IV consists of secondary publications on topics such as missiles, aeronautics, lunar and planetary sciences, extraterrestrial life, remote sensing, meteor orbits/dust and astrophysics, symposium proceedings, materials related to computing (including the Illiac IV, Cray I, Cray-IS and VAX computers and ARPANET), newsletters (both published by NASA and by outside entities) and other general materials.
Container List
- I: Mission Analysis Records, 1965-1974
  - Saturn V, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Saturn IB, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Burner II, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Analytical Cost/Performance Model for the Analysis of the Long Duration Manned Space Missions, Final Report, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Final Report, Service Module Upper Stage, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Planetary Programs, Analysis of Titan III F Family Capability for the Mars 1973 Type 1 Mission, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - S-5 Study, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - SLV, General Dynamics, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1 Centaur Sizing Study for Titan IIID and IIIB, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Proposal for Systems Modeling and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment Study, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Systems Modeling and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Contracts, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Systems Modeling and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Proposal Documents, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Technical Reports, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NASA Space Shuttle Task Group Report, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Solid/Agena Launch Vehicle System, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Titan III, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The UA1207 First Stage Solid Rocket Motor Technical Report, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - AIAA Paper, The Nuclear Shuttle for Interorbital and Transplanetary Applications, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Impact of the Space Shuttle on Satellite Payloads, Technical Memorandum, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Saturn IB, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Space Shuttle Engineering Memoranda, Lockheed Missiles and Space Company, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Study of Methodology and Model Development for Minimizing Space Program Costs, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1970 (1 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1970 (2 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1970 (3 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1970 (4 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Final Reports, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Launch Vehicle Study for NASA Missions, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mission Analysis of Shuttle Operations Between Earth and the Moon, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Comparative Evolution of Space Transportation Concepts, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Logic Checkout and Production Exercising of Space Program Optimal Assignment Model, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Methodologies for Optimal Resource Allocation to the National Space Program and New Space Utilization, Final Report, 1971 (1 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Methodologies for Optimal Resource Allocation to the National Space Program and New Space Utilization, Final Report, 1971 (2 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Methodologies for Optimal Resource Allocation to the National Space Program and New Space Utilization, Final Report, 1971 (3 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Payload Effects Analysis Study, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Probabilistic Systems Modeling and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Final Report, Volume 1, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Probabilistic Systems Modeling and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Final Report, Volume 2, 1971 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Probabilistic Systems Modeling and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Final Report, Volume 2, 1971 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1971 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, Reports and Schedules, 1971 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Task Report, Study of Systems and Cost/Performance Methodologies for Optimization of Vehicle Assignment, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Utilization of Halo Orbits in Advance Lunar Operations, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Space Applications Program Review, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Space Applications Program, Appendices, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Study of Computer Data Transfer Via Satellite, Monthly Report and Final Report, 1974 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Study of Computer Data Transfer Via Satellite, Monthly Report and Final Report, 1974 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Study of Computer Data Transfer Via Satellite, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - IDAS comparison Matrices, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mission Analysis Humor, undated (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mission Analysis Humor, undated (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Planetary Programs, Launch Vehicle Appendix, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- II: Technology Applications Records, 1974-1998
  - Earth Resources Program, Revised Project Plan, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Image Selection System, M. A. Knutson et al., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Satellite On-Board Processing for Earth Resources Data, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - User Dissemination Concepts for Earth Resources, Final Report, 1976 (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - User Dissemination Concepts for Earth Resources, Final Report, 1976 (2 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - User Dissemination Concepts for Earth Resources, Final Report, 1976 (3 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - User Dissemination Concepts for Earth Resources, Final Report, 1976 (4 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - User Dissemination Concepts for Earth Resources, Final Report, 1976 (5 of 5) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP) memoranda, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Landsat Newsletter: Signature, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Institute for Advanced Computation, Landsat Image Processing Documentation, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP) Summary Reports, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter: Pixel Facts, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - CZCS Coastal Zone Color Scanner Investigations Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Institute for Advanced Computation, Landsat Imaging Program Descriptions and User Guides, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Institute for Advanced Computation, Landsat Image Processing, Final Report, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP) Review, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP) Training Program, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Landsat, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newsletter: Landsat Data User Notes, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newsletter: Plain Brown Wrapper, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Western Regional Remote Sensing Conference Proceedings, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Western Regional Applications Program (WRAP) Publications, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 1982 Report: Renewable Resources Remote Sensing Research Program (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Earth Resources Bibliography, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Land-Related Global Habitability Science Issues, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Airborne Science and Applications Program, 20th Anniversary, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Code LX Extraterrestrial Research Division Roster, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - ECOSAT Research Activity and Publication Update, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Life Science Division Roster, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - ECOSAT Branch Strategy Planning Document, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - ECOSAT Branch, Annual Report, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - NASA Earth Systems Science Overview, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Rosters, 1987-1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - ECOSAT Branch, Annual Report, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Newsletter: What on Earth, 1989-1995 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Newsletter: What on Earth, 1989-1995 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence: ECOSAT Branch, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Earth Systems Science Division, Annual Reports, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Earth Systems Science Division, Annual Reports, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Earth Systems Science Division, Annual Reports, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Mission to Planet Earth Call for Proposals, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - An Exercise in Automated Analysis of Remotely Sensed Data, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Center for Health Applications of Aerospace Related Technologies, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
- III: NASA Ames Administrative Records, 1971-2001
  - Clippings, Ephemera, 1958-1995 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous Project Management Documents, 1968-1991 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Administrative Memoranda, 1971-2001 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Personal, Commendations, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Active Job Order Numbers, Fiscal Year, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - NASA Excellence Teams at Ames Research Center: A Dynamic Approach to Productivity, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Ames Human Resources Division Publications, 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - NASA Strategic Plan, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Awards, Length of Service Honors, 1992-1999 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Human Resources-Related Publications and Memoranda, 1994-1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ames, "State of the Center,", 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- IV: General/Reference Publications, 1961-1999
  - Missiles and Rockets: The Missile Space Weekly, November 27, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reference Publications, 1962-1971 (1 of 5) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reference Publications, 1962-1971 (2 of 5) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reference Publications, 1962-1971 (3 of 5) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reference Publications, 1962-1971 (4 of 5) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reference Publications, 1962-1971 (5 of 5) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Computer Program Documentation Time Phasing Program (TIPP), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - AIAA Journal Subject and Author Indexes, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Iliac IV, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - NASA Human Interest Files, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Safe Living with Less Energy, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - ARPANET, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Bits Pieces, The Economics Press, Inc., 1975 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Calspan Corporation Annual Report, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - CRAY I, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newsletter: Logist-O-Gram, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Inventories of Irrigated Lands in Southern Idaho Using Various Remote Sensing Techniques, R.C. Heller and K.A. Johnson, September 30, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Newsletter: Institute for Advanced Computing, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Institute for Advanced Computation, Magnetic Tape (I4) Facility Descriptions, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Institute for Advanced Computation, Unicon File System, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Newsletter: Vax News, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Newsletter: NASA Newsline, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - CRAY-IS, Coding Techniques for Vectorization, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Newsletter: CCF (Central Computer Facility) Bulletin, 1982-1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Newsletter: NSSDC (National Space Science Data Center) News, 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Newsletter: Life Lines, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Newsletter: On Line, 1987-1990 (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Newsletter: On Line, 1991 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Directory of Applications Software for Cray Supercomputers, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Newsletter: On Target, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Newsletter: Interface, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - The Importance of "Small" Science, G. Dalrymple, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Newsletter: Sun News, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Newsletter: Moffett Beacon, September-October 1994 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Newsletter: Tae + Bulletin, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Astrobiology Workshop Final Report, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Newsletter: NFFE, April-May 1996 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Y2K Desktop Readiness Initiative, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - The Eros Data Center, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Hydrology and Geology of the Chicxulub Structure: A Possible Buried K/T Impact Crater in Yukatan, Mexico, Draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)